Good evening to, today's דף daf is ע"ד, ayin daled, 74. We're
in the middle of a classic section of
אגדתא Aggadata around sea stories, but obviously sort of goes even further
and some of the more fantastic אגדתות Aggadatas in the גמרא. Gemara.
And we pick up at the bottom of ע"ג עמוד ב'. ayin
gimmel amud bet.
And it's אמר לי, amar li, last line of ע"ג עמוד ב'.
ayin gimmel amud bet. This is about רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah
bar Bar Chana that said that he once encountered a an Arab,
a Bedouin and here are some of the things that this Bedouin
showed him,
some mysteries and some secrets for people who knew the wilderness and
the desert and so on. So אמר לי, amar li, he said
to me, תא אחוי לך כמה, ta achvei lach kam, let me
show you
מתי מדבר, mesei midbar, those who died in the desert. You know,
those, the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael that died in their 40 years
of wandering, I know where they're buried. So אזלי חזיתינהו, azli chazitinhu,
I
went, we went, he showed them to me. ודמו כמאן דמבסמי, vedamu
keman demivsemi, and they looked like they were a little drunk. That's
what the רשב"ם Rashbam says, like they had a smile on their
face. Okay.
וגנו אפרקיד, veganu aparkid, and they were lying down on their back.
Actually there's an interesting debate whether אפרקיד aparkid means on their front
or on their back, but based on this גמרא, Gemara, because he
was
seeing their face, it seems very clear that it means they were
lying on their back. Okay. והוה זקיפא ברכיה דחד מינייהו. vahavei zekifa
barchei dechad mineihu. Now one of them,
their knees were raised. Their legs were raised, their knees were raised.
ועייל טייעא תותי ברכיה, va'ayal taya tusei barchei, and a nomad was
able to go under their raised leg. I mean they were obviously,
now they were like giants, they were gigantic. כי רכיב גמלא וזקיפא
רומחיה. kirachiv gamla vezekifa rumchei. Like riding a camel
with his
spear upright. Okay, so you know, he had like I don't know,
a 50 foot clearance. Okay. So here you had like the bent
knee of one of these people who died in the wilderness and
there was a sign above that said clearance 50 foot. And then
the camel rider with the spear was able to go under it.
Okay. ולא נגע ביה, velo naga bei, and didn't bump into
it. ולא נגע ביה. velo naga bei. פסקי חד קרנא דתכילתא דחד
מינייהו. paski chad karna detcheilesa dechad mineihu. Now I figured heck as
long as I'm here, it's all very wondrous and all of that,
but what's most important to me is let's see if we can
learn some הלכה halacha from how they acted. So what I did
was I cut off the corner of one of their ציצית tzitzis
in order that I could see like how was it that they
made ציצית. tzitzis. Okay, you know, ציצית tzitzis is one of the
things in the תורה. Torah. I mean there's a few obviously, but
like the תורה Torah defines it in like one word, ועשו להם
ציצית, ve'asu lachem tzitzis, right, על כנפי בגדיהם, al kanfei bigdeichem, right.
And then it says כנף פתיל תכלת, knaf pesil tcheiles, the corner
a string of תכלת. tcheiles. But anyway, there's so it's like a
lot, you know, why not go to the people who actually first
experienced the command and go ahead and see how they made their
ציצית. tzitzis. So פסקי חד קרנא דתכילתא דחד מינייהו. paski chad karna
detcheilesa dechad mineihu. I cut off the corner of one of their
literally תכלת tcheiles is the blue string, but you know, one of
their ציצית, tzitzis, in order to take it back so we could
have some evidence about what they did. And maybe also want to
see how they made תכלת. tcheiles. Okay. I mean in the time
of the גמרא Gemara they knew how to make תכלת. tcheiles. ולא
הוה מסתגי לן. velo hava mistagyei lan. And we weren't able to
travel forth. Now based on before that it said that they were
gigantic, you maybe it was too heavy, it was like the grapes,
you needed maybe 10 spies to 8 spies to carry it or
something. Anyway. But he stole something.
I know.
So anyway, but that's it's not going to be about its weight.
אמר לי, amar li, so this Arab nomad said to me,
דילמא שקלת מידי מינייהו? dilma shaklas midi mineihu? Like we for some
reason we like felt like we were glued to our place. So
then he said to me is it possible you tried to take
something from them? Why? Because apparently he didn't know initially. אהדריה, hadrei,
go put it back. דגמירי, degamiri, we have a tradition דמאן דשקיל
מידי מינייהו, deman deshakeil midi mineihu, if somebody takes something from them,
לא מסתגי ליה. lo mistagyei lei. He won't be able to move.
אזלי, azli, I mean you know, I guess he could move somewhat,
you got you were able to
take from whom?
From the dead of the from
the
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael that died in the wilderness.
He took it off the corpse.
Off the corpse, yes. He took the ציצית tzitzis off the corpse
of one of the bodies. Okay, and then he said oh, that's
why we can't move forward because we have a tradition, you know,
sort of like the same way the pharaohs in their tombs if
you were to raid the tomb like you're cursed. So here too
you've got the dead of the wilderness and if you try to
take anything from them you won't you'll be stuck in your place.
So they didn't פסול pasul the ציצית tzitzis when they buried them
did they the way.
So I'm going to talk about that. That's what the big תוספות
Tosafos is about. אזלי, azli, I went, אהדרתיה. hadristei. I returned it,
the ציצית tzitzis to the corpse. והדר מסתגי לן. ve'hadar mistagyei lan.
And then we were able to move forward. כי אתאי לקמיה דרבנן,
ki asai lekamei derabbanan, then when I came back to the rabbis
in the academy, in the בית מדרש, beis medrash, אמרו לי, amri
lei, they said to me. me כל אבא חמרא. kol abba chamra.
Now this his name was אבא בר בר חנה. Abba bar Bar
Chana. So they said they sort of mocked me רבה בר בר
חנה Rabba bar Bar Chana excuse me רבה Rabba is רב אבא.
Rav Abba. So his actual first name was אבא, Abba, okay? So
they said to me they were mocked me. They said כל אבא
חמרא, kol abba chamra, every every אבא Abba is a donkey, okay?
Or so and obviously it sort of alliterates רבה בר בר חנה,
Rabba bar Bar Chana, אבא, Abba, רבה בר בר חנה, Rabba bar
Bar Chana, אבא חמרא, Abba Chamra, okay? So you could sort of
see that's what the kids at the schoolyard used to call me.
Instead of calling me רבה בר בר חנה, Rabba bar Bar Chana,
they called me they called me אבא חמרא, Abba Chamra, okay? So
anyway every אבא's Abba a donkey וכל בר בר חנה סכסא v'kol
Bar Bar Chana sachsa and every בר בר חנה Bar Bar Chana
is a fool, okay? So you're a donkey and a you're and
a fool. You're a donkey. אמרו ליה amru lei that was a
stupid thing you were trying to do, okay? אמרו ליה amru lei
so למאי הלכתא עבדת הכי? l'mai hilchasa avdas hachi? Why you know
for what purpose were you trying to cut the ציצית tzitzis and
to bring it? למדע l'meda to know איכא בית שמאי איכא בית
הלל. ika Beis Shammai ika Beis Hillel. There's a whole all these
debates between בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel how
to make ציצית. tzitzis. So you wanted to see how they פסקן.
pasken. You know it's just like when we now recovered the תפילין
tefillin in מצדה. Masada. So we figured oh now we can know
if they have if they were like רש"י Rashi or רבינו תם.
Rabbeinu Tam. And they found both pairs of תפילין. tefillin. Oh I'm
serious they did. All in מצדה, Masada, you know in terms of
this it was an ancient debate about what are the order of
the פרשיות. parshiyos. So maybe they would have found the same thing
then you should have said you shouldn't just take one pair ציצית,
tzitzis, you should have taken a sampling or array so we could
have seen. Anyway why did you want to take it? To know
whether it's like בית הלל Beis Hillel or בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
So איבעי לך לממני חוטין ולממני חוליות. ibayei lach l'mimni chutin ul'mimni
chulyos. Then you know so if that's true then even if you
weren't able to take it and you had to return it you
could have you should have counted the number of strings and counted
the number you know the חוליות chulyos are like the the wraps
around you know the twists around you do the main strings the
sections of wrappings you should have counted it. So presumably you should
have counted it what they were saying was if you were going
to restore it then you know it's not like all or nothing
like don't bring back the evidence or don't have anything to tell
us. Like before you restored it you could have taken some notes
you could have you know reported it to us. Oh so that's
the... you could have taken a picture by the way raises interesting
questions right about like the like about the development of הלכה. halacha.
How much can we use archaeology and history to determine הלכה halacha
questions? Right? Like let's say like going back to this here case
about what do you call it of נו nu of מצדה, Masada,
you know so they measured the size of the מקואות mikvaos there
because obviously water was was scarce. So obviously the assumption is that
the מקוה's mikvah only going to be the bare minimum size and
based on that size of the מקוה mikvah you can now know
the size of a lot of שיעורים shiurim how they were assessed
at the time of בית שני. Bayis Sheni. So how much does
that sort of define הלכה halacha issues? Right? How much does archaeology,
history, whatever, you know define הלכה halacha issues? Is it an acceptable
source? How much does the sort of הלכה, halacha, you know legal
truth work independently of historical truth, etc.?
So anyway evidence you know supplants takes the place of שני עדים,
shnei eidim, right?
Well that's yeah but that's like a different question. This is this
sort of recognizes that the way law develops might not you know
there might be like you know what becomes canonical what becomes פסקנד,
paskened, right? If we wind up having the debate בית הלל בית
שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai we פסקן pasken one way and then
there was evidence like הלכה כבית הלל halacha k'Beis Hillel but then
there was evidence that 2,000 years ago the practice was like בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. Does it mean בית הלל's Beis Hillel wrong or
does it mean okay historically that's the way it was but now
we פסקן pasken otherwise? So I think this is just interesting in
terms of I mean obviously this is אגדתא agadata but like the
assumption of it is interesting. Yes.
You have a similar issue with when a manuscript that was thought
lost is rediscovered.
Right exactly what manuscripts become canonical, what if we find you know
that there have been mistakes in manuscripts? I mean there's all these
interesting questions of science and הלכה halacha and history and הלכה. halacha.
Okay anyway now so I don't so I well what I did
do what I will share is תוספות Tosafos which is a הלכה
halacha analysis of this. But David you want to share with us
what your footnote says about any מהרש"א, Maharsha, yeah
מהרש"א. Maharsha. Yeah.
Those was the תורה Torah given at סיני Sinai must be surrounded
by a fence safeguard against any transgression. Yeah.
This is about the scorpion I'm sorry.
Oh no we're not there yet we're not up to any scorpions
yet.
I just had a note about it didn't have any
it didn't have any like metaphorical explanation about this whole story. I
mean the question about how big they were obviously suggests the question
you know about like their spiritual greatness which is like a common
trope and a common theme. Right? I don't know about stealing something
or taking something from them and not going forward, you know it
seems to have some like you know metaphoric possibilities which is funny
right because like we take you know if you think about it
with the מסורה mesorah we have passed down from them that allows
us to move forward, you know but why is it taking some
physical
artifact doesn't allow us? Maybe that part gets to this question that
I'm raising about how much is הלכה Halacha rooted in historical evidence
of the past as opposed to a new ability to move forward
and the development—ongoing תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh development of
הלכה—is Halacha that we're not rooted in the
past. We start in the past. We are rooted in the past.
We start in the past, but we're not sort of limited to
that. And then we're able to sort of move forward from there.
So yes. חדש ימינו כקדם.
Chadesh yameinu k'kedem. Exactly. A contradiction.
Right.
How do you חדש כקדם? chadesh k'kedem? Right.
Right, right, right. Exactly. So maybe that's this, about like don't let—we
shouldn't be buried with the past, right? We have to sort of
be rooted in it but move forward. So תוספות Tosafot raises this
whole issue of the ציצית. tzitzit.
Because according to the evidence in the גמרא, Gemara, it seems to
be that they buried the dead with the ציצית. tzitzit. And this
seems consistent with this. But תוספות Tosafot says this is not really
evidence to that, because the famous story about how they died in
the wilderness was that they dug their own graves and they went
to lie down and then some would get—and then the next morning
some would get up and some would stay there. So since they
were lying down with their clothes before while they were still alive,
they still had their ציצית tzitzit on. So this גמרא Gemara is
not direct evidence that they would bury the dead with their ציצית,
tzitzit, but תוספות Tosafot says there are other גמרות Gemarot that seem
to say that. And the problem is, is that the מנהג minhag
was that actually the opposite, that you tear the ציצית tzitzit from
the garment, you don't bury the dead with ציצית. tzitzit. So תוספות
Tosafot wants to know how to sort of reconcile those two. One
basic answer which תוספות Tosafot sort of alludes to here but he
says elsewhere is that it's a difference between a בבל Bavel practice
and an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael practice. The בבל Bavel practice was
to bury the dead with the ציצית, tzitzit, the ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael practice was not to, and אשכנזים Ashkenazim in particular are sometimes
influenced by ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael practices even when they diverge from
the בבלי. Bavli. So, but תוספות Tosafot here, if you want to
see some answers in this,
תוספות Tosafot says the following.
It's like if you see the line that's like halfway down the
narrow line in תוספות, Tosafot, the line that begins with the parentheses
שבת דף ל, Shabbos daf lamed, okay? So you go one line
down from there, you see those parentheses that begin with that line.
He says: אבל קשה על המנהג שנוהגים להסיר ציצית מהטליתות מטליתות של
מתים. Aval kasha al haminhag shenohagim l'hasir tzitzit mehatallitot meitallitot shel meitim.
How is it that we remove the ציצית, tzitzit, given that the
evidence in the גמרא Gemara is that you would bury the dead
with ציצית? tzitzit? ואומר רבינו תם ששמע מזקני לותיר—Lotharingia—שלו לפי שציצית עדות
שקיים כל kol התורה. That ציצית tzitzit עולה תר. olei taf-resh. The
גימטריא gematria of ציצית tzitzit is six hundred, וח' חוטין וה' קשרים
veches chutin v'hei ksharim and the eight strings and the
five knots, הוי תרי"ג. havei taryag. So ציצית tzitzit are supposed to
remind you of the תורה, Torah, of the מצוות. mitzvot. So they
would bury them as a sort of symbolic saying, this person was
מקיים mekayeim all the מצוות mitzvot of the תורה. Torah. ועכשיו שאין
חשובים כל כך הרי הוא כעין עדות שקר. Ve'achshav she'ein chashuvim kol
kach harei hu k'ein eidut sheker. So now we're not at the
same מדריגה. madreigah. So that's one explanation how,
maybe the מנהגים minhagim changed and it gives some explanation why the
מנהגים minhagim changed. Changed? Exactly. והכי נמי דרשינן במדרש: Vehacha nami darshinan
b'Midrash: ועשו להם ציצית לדורותם, V'asu lahem tzitzit l'dorotam, לדור תם. l'dor
tam.
So like if you're like perfect or something. Okay. So that's one
answer, a change because we're no longer can make a statement like
we're מקיים כל התורה כולה. mekayeim kol haTorah kullah. ואומר רי—now V'omer
Ri here's another explanation, these are very interesting because they basically, a
number of them rather than sort of saying geographic בבלי-ירושלמי, Bavli-Yerushalmi,
suggest a historic change over time. ואומר רי דבימיהם היו כולם מקיימים
מצות ציצית—לפי שהיה לכולם טליתות של ארבע כנפות.
Everybody would regularly wear ציצית, tzitzit, because their standard garments had four
corners. Technically there's no obligation to put on a garment with four
corners with ציצית. tzitzit. It's if you're wearing a four-cornered garment, you
put ציצית tzitzit on it. So he said then, everybody, that was
the standard garment, ולכך היו עושים להם אפילו במותם. ulekach hayu osim
lahem afilu bemotam. So if your standard garment, if it's not just
a ritual garment, if your standard garment has four corners, then you
have to put ציצית tzitzit on it. It's like you have to
make sure your garment doesn't have שעטנז, sha'atnez, and you have to
make sure that if it's got four corners it has ציצית. tzitzit.
So it wasn't sort of a ritual garment, it was just what
you do on a normal garment. So burying people in their ציצית,
tzitzit, it's a very interesting insight. Burying people in their ציצית tzitzit
was not 'we're going to bury them with this
ritual object called a טלית.' tallit. We're just burying them in their
clothes, but their clothes happened to have ציצית tzitzit on them. Of
course the funny thing is, like even the תכריכין, tachrichin, like even
the shrouds were four corners? Maybe, if their standard sort of garments
were four corners. But anyway, but it wasn't seen as much as
an intentional burying with a ritual item. ולכך היו עושים להם אפילו
במותם. ulekach hayu osim lahem afilu bemotam. אבל עכשיו שאין לכולנו בחייהם—nowadays
Aval achshav she'ein l'kulanu bechayeihem
that many people don't wear ציצית tzitzit in general—now that seems not
only like their standard garments didn't have four corners, but it seems
like a lot of people might have spent their whole lives and
saying I never wore a garment. and never wore garment with four
corners, so I never had to put on ציצית. tzitzit. So now
that it is very widespread that people don't wear ציצית, tzitzit, not
because they're violating, but because they're not wearing those types of garments,
אין לעשות בהן, ein la'asot bahen, אפילו מי שהיה לו בחייו, afilu
mi shehayah lo bechayav, even if there was somebody who did wear
ציצית tzitzit in his life, שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו, shelo
levayesh et mi she'ein lo, you know, not to make that person
stand out. So it's interesting, it's basically, I mean, whether he's sort
of saying this difference of what is it seen of as a
ritual garment or סתם stam a garment, or is he sort of
saying, you know, at a time when everybody wore ציצית, tzitzit, we
bury people with ציצית, tzitzit, now that it's rare, it would sort
of, you know, mark a difference between people in their deaths. So
we don't want to sort of do that. I also wonder what
he means that he says people don't wear
ציצית. tzitzit. Did he mean like even when they דאווען, daven, I
mean, I think it's an interesting question, right, when the practice came
to wear like דאווקא davka a טלית tallit לצורך תפילה. l'tzorech tefillah.
I mean, there's a lot about being מתעטף בטלית mit'atef b'tallit when
you're wearing, when you're דאווען-ing daven-ing already in the גמרא. Gemara. So
exactly,
exactly, certainly a שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur would.
I was just looking at, I don't remember exactly what period it
was but some pretty early on that shows people wearing, or shows,
I think the earlier ones show just the שליח shaliach people are
wearing. Right. And the later ones show everyone.
Everyone wearing, interesting, so that's what we were sort of, yeah, saying
like מתעטף בטלית, mit'atef b'tallit, at least the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur
or whatever. So certainly like during תפילה לעני כי יעטוף. tefillah l'ani
ki ya'atof. Okay, but of course that doesn't necessarily have to mean
being עוטף otef with a טלית, tallit, it could just mean wrapping
yourself with like, you know, whatever garment or whatever. But anyway, it's
interesting hearing תוספות Tosafot say, oh, nowadays there are people that don't
wear ציצית tzitzit in their lives, right, does he mean ever, does
he mean, yeah.
Well, that gets to the point, why bother wearing a טלית גדול?
tallit gadol? I wear a טלית קטן tallit katan all the time.
Yeah. I've already, I'm fulfilling the מצוה. mitzvah.
Well, that's a different story. According to many גאונים, Geonim, you're not
יוצא yotzei with a טלית קטן tallit katan because it's not a
real garment, that only a garment that you wrap yourself with is
considered to be a full garment. So, yeah.
It doesn't make the question just, you know, there are really certain
communities where like everyone wears ציצית. tzitzit. Yeah. You know, then would
we be able to bury
people with ציצית?
tzitzit? Yeah. So right. So then maybe the מנהג minhag could change
back. Yeah, Rabbi Dov, what did you want to say?
Well, just first, I mean, my understanding was that the טלית גדול
tallit gadol during תפילה tefillah was a way of giving more כבוד
kavod to the תפילות tefillot of the בית כנסת. Beit Knesset. Right.
I
thought ספרדים Sefardim say להתעטף בציצית l'hitatef b'tzitzit and...
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
So why did they פסל pasel the ציצית? tzitzit?
Yeah, what was the idea of like wearing them and then ripping
them off? Like that's also...
I don't mean the סרדין, sardin, I mean in general.
I know, that's interesting. Meaning, it's one thing to say you don't
bury with ציצית, tzitzit, it's another thing to say you bury and
then you rip it off. I mean, clearly there's obviously a powerful
symbolic statement of like, you know, like this statement in the גמרא,
Gemara, כיון שמת אדם נעשה חפשי מן המצוות, keivan shemet adam na'aseh
chofshi min hamitzvot, right, when you die you now are free from
מצוות, mitzvot, like it's sort of saying, it's also very symbolic, it's
almost like tearing קריעה, keriah, you know, something is being ripped from
you and the מת met is being sort of ripped from the
life of the living and the life of
מצוות. mitzvot. So powerful symbolism there, you know. I mean, to me
it's actually, it's a little spooky thinking about burying somebody in their
ציצית. tzitzit. It's a little too, I don't know, like what's it
supposed to say? They're going to die and then they're going to
go up to heaven and still be wearing ציצית. tzitzit. Exactly.
Exactly.
It's like, you know, the whole point about like you bury in
a, you know, in a wood box, everything's sort of, it's the
exact opposite of preserving, it's all about restoring to the earth. Now
one of the ideas that תוספות Tosafot said is that the idea
is well, if at the time of תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim the
צדיקים tzadikim are going to rise up in the garments that they
were buried in, so they want to be able to rise up
with their ציצית tzitzit on like at that time. But they ripped
them off, it won't help. Well, no, well now, he's talking about
the original practice. So it's interesting to think about sort of the
different types of symbolisms there. Let's just read a little bit more,
just read, one more, if you go down a little line he
says, אנו סומכין על מסכת שמחות, anu somchin al masechet smachot, it's
sort of like, like 10 lines from the bottom where it says
there in the parenthesis פרק יב. perek yud bet. Yeah, we have
מסכת שמחות, masechet smachot, which is like a גאוני Geonic work. דאמרינן
d'amrinan or whatever, it's a collection of earlier work. Was it? I
was just thinking. If you want to we could read it, it
was just not directly relevant.
All right, fine. I'll read it then. Okay, he says like this.
אבל עתה שאין נוהגין כן אין לעשות בהן אפילו מי שהיה לו
בחייו שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו. aval ata she'ein nohagin ken
ein la'asot bahen afilu mi shehayah lo bechayav shelo levayesh et mi
she'ein lo. כעניין זה מצינו פרק בתרא דנידה, k'inyan zeh matzinu perek
batra d'niddah, בראשונה היו מטבילין כלים על גבי נשים נידות מתות, berishonah
hayu matbilin kelim al gabei nashim niddot metot, so they would used
to immerse women who had died while they were a נידה, niddah,
they would immerse them before burying them. And, and while we're doing
an immersion, we might as well do our טבילת כלים tevilat kelim
at the same time. התחילו חיות מתביישות, hitchilu chayot mitbayshot, that caused
embarrassment for the live women. Anyway, so all that תוספות Tosafot without
going into that, if you're interested you could look at that. Anyway,
he's just sort of making a statement about not to make differences
during death, okay, in certain rituals during death. ובעוד אנו סומכין על
מסכת שמחות דאמרינן אבא שאול בן בתניס.
u'v'od anu somchin al masechet
smachot
d'amrinan Abba Shaul ben Bitnis. ציווה את בניו קברוהו תחת מרגלותיו של
אבא והטילו תכלת מהאפיליוני. tzivva et banav kevuruhu tachat margelotav shel abba
ve-hatilu tchelet me-ha-apilyoni. So and put,
now the question is there's a והטילו תכלת, ve-hatilu tchelet, normally means
put ציצית, tzitzit, but then it should be באפיליוני ba-apilyoni in my
garment, but the
מהאפיליוני, me-ha-apilyoni, so פירוש מטליתו. perush mi-talito. ויש לגרוס התירו, v-yesh ligros
hitiro, not put תכלת tchelet but remove it. So we rely ourselves
on מסכת שמחות, Masekhet Semachot, which maybe does also say put on
ציצית tzitzit but we're going to read it to say take off
the ציצית. tzitzit. Okay. מהא, me-ha, from. So anyway maybe there's a
different source and that's sort of an indication that it's maybe a
בבלי Bavli tradition as opposed to an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael tradition.
בבלי Bavli tradition with ציצית, tzitzit, maybe an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
tradition without. And here would be the idea of actively removing. Okay.
רבינו חיים כהן Rabbeinu Chaim Kohen said it because קיימא לן kayma
lan like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that said מצוות בטלות לעתיד לבוא.
mitzvot betelot le-atid lavo. Ah, the reason why we tear the ציצית
tzitzit is because in the future, in the time of תחיית המתים,
techiyat ha-metim, there won't be any מצוות mitzvot anymore. So that's a
pretty wild theological statement. There'll be no מצוות mitzvot in the time
of, you know, in the future ימות המשיח yemot ha-mashiach when the
dead rise up. So they're going to not need their ציצית tzitzit
when they rise up, so that's why you remove them.
The whole thing.
Yeah. והא דמנחות ve-ha de-Menachot
and the other גמרא Gemara that says that you bury the dead
with their ציצית tzitzit is אליבא דשמואל aliba de-Shmuel דאמר אין בטלות,
de-amar ein betelot, that says that in the future when they rise
up the מצוות mitzvot will still be in practice. ולכך צריך שיהיה
בו ציצית, u-lekhakh tzarikh she-yehe bo tzitzit, and therefore you need the
ציצית, tzitzit, שעתידין צדיקים שיעמדו במלבושיהם, she-atidin tzaddikim she-yaamdu bi-levusheihem,
that they're going to rise up with the garments they were buried
in. ואם יסירו לו הציצית במותו נמצא שלעתיד יעמוד בלא ציצית. v-im
yasiru lo ha-tzitzit be-moto nimtza she-le-atid yaamod belo tzitzit. Then when they
rise up they won't have the ציצית. tzitzit. Okay and then he
goes on and that's basically, that's basically it for the בבלי Bavli
tradition because we actively remove. Right.
I understand, I understand.
I think the symbolism of actively removing them is very powerful. But
the point is you have to make it work together with the
indications in the בבלי Bavli that they used to bury the dead
with their ציצית. tzitzit. Right. I see.
This phrase
ציווה את בניו קברוהו תחת מרגלותיו של
אבא,
tzivva et banav kevuruhu tachat margelotav shel
abba,
meaning what, that's like the way the grave was organized?
I think so, like in the כוך kuch and the... yeah exactly.
But then he says at the end, אשר לשים ציצית בטלית של
מת. Asher lasim tzitzit be-talit shel met. He says it says that,
he says it says that? Where? Last line of the תוספות. Tosafot.
ולא הוצרך מעולם להשים וכן נוהגים בארץ
אשכנז, v-lo hu-tzrakh me-olam le-hasim ve-khen
nohagim be-Eretz
Ashkenaz, wait
a minute... ודי רמינא שמשימין
ציצית
ומסלקין אותו מיד להודיע שקיים מצוות ציצית לפי שבגד חדש v-dai ramina
she-masimin tzitzit u-mesalkin oto mi-yad le-hodia she-kiyem mitzvat tzitzit lefi
she-beged chadash etc.
so when he has שמשימין she-masimin it means שמשימין she-masimin and then
removing.
So not cutting a corner.
Right, probably not cutting, maybe not cutting a corner. Okay, back to
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay since I don't have a good explanation on
the אגדתא, Aggadata, I just figured we'll learn some הלכה. Halakha.
Yeah, I'm just going to officially speak or put this on the
record. Yes. This was the strangest מנהג minhag ever. Like, oh, she
just died נידה, niddah, let's bring the calendar and the
Friday.
I know that. So okay moving on, when we learn נידה niddah
we can discuss it more. Moving on. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay אמר ליה, amar lei, back to the גמרא
Gemara about ten lines down, ten lines from the top, אמר ליה,
amar lei, אמר לי, amar li, whatever this Arab nomad said to
me, תא אחוי לך האי סיני. ta achvi lach hai Sinai. Come,
let me show you Mount Sinai. Okay that was also in the
wilderness, in the desert. אזלי חזאי דהדרא ליה עקרבא, azli chazai de-hadra
lei akrava, that it was surrounded by scorpions, וקיימא כחמרי חיורתא, v-kayma
ki-chamrei chivrata, and they were sort of and they looked they were
these huge scorpions the size of white donkeys.
Oh, white donkeys are particularly vicious.
Oh that's right, white donkeys are vicious. You never recover.
Exactly, that's correct, the גמרא Gemara says you don't recover from the
bite of a white donkey. שמעת בת קול שאומרת shama'at bat kol
she-omeret and I heard a heavenly voice saying אוי לי שנשבעתי, oy
li she-nishbati,
woe to me that I took an, because of the oath that
I took, ועכשיו שנשבעתי מי מפר לי, v-akhshav she-nishbati mi mefer li,
and now that I got of taken this oath who can annul
it for me?
So what oath are we talking about?
When I came back to the rabbis in the בית מדרש, Beit
Midrash, they said to me כל אבא חמרא וכל בר בר חנה
סיכלא, kol Abba chamra ve-khol Bar Bar Chana sikhla, and here we
have the donkey already mentioned in this story, so this again רבה
בר בר חנה, Rabbah Bar Bar Chana, every Abba's a donkey and
every Bar Bar Chana is a fool. Now I'm guessing by the
way they said the reason כל was so that they weren't directly
calling him a name, they were just making a statement about the
class. All right, not about him personally, but anyway, saying you were
an idiot. היה לך לומר מופר לך. haya lekha lomar mufar lakh.
God was asking somebody to be מתיר matir his נדר, neder, you
could have been מתיר matir God's נדר. neder.
So the גמרא Gemara says, well, God was inviting it. What? I
exactly, exactly. והוא סבר, ve-hu savar, now רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah
Bar Bar Chana who wasn't מתיר matir God's נדר neder thought דילמא
שבועתא דמבולא היא, dilma shevuata de-mabula hi, what נדר, neder, what שבועה
shevuah are we talking about? So he thought maybe it was God's
שבועה shvua that he was not going to bring another מבול mabbul
to the world. So he didn't want to מתיר matir that נדר.
neder. Maybe God was so angry with the people's deeds that God
wanted to flood the world and he wasn't going to participate in
letting God do that. רבנן Rabbanan and the rabbis, what שבועה shvua
did they think God was talking about? So, איי גדין אוי לי
למי לי? Ay gadin oy li lami li? Why was he saying
woe to me? Clearly God would not feel woe that he could
not wipe out the world, so it must be something that God
is pained about. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, I think the standard
explanation is that it's about to send the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
into exile. So God suffers together with the suffering of בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael and he feels and he empathizes and that's why it's
woe to me about that שבועה. shvua. So by the way, couple
things about this. Number one is תוספות Tosfot has an interesting discussion
about
whether the assumption of this גמרא Gemara is that you need another
party to מתיר matir a נדר. neder. Okay? But תוספות Tosfot quotes
another גמרא Gemara that sounds like at least God could מתיר matir
his own נדר. neder. So do you always need another party to
מתיר matir a שבועה shvua or נדר? neder? Number one. But I
also want to say that
it's not in this גמרא Gemara per se, but the idea that
a human being could מתיר matir God's נדר. neder. There is one
of the most, I don't know, wild or
radical מדרשים. Midrashim. It says by the פסוק, passuk, I forget if
it's on the פרשה parsha of התרת נדרים Hatarat Nedarim or it's
anyway, but when it says the פסוק passuk that says משה איש
האלוהים, Moshe ish ha-Elokim, Moses the man of God, it reads the
word איש ish as husband and it says משה Moshe is God's
husband, which is already fascinating because it casts God as the female,
and it says the same way a husband can מתיר matir his
wife's נדר neder and שבועה, shvua, משה Moshe could מתיר matir a
שבועה shvua that God took. Okay? So it says אישה יקימנו ואישה
יפרנו. Ishah yekimenu v'ishah yeferenu. So therefore, and then it leads to
a whole idea about צדיק גוזר והקדוש ברוך הוא מקיים Tzaddik gozer
v'ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu mekayem and anything God says a צדיק Tzaddik can
override based on this like משה איש האלוהים. Moshe ish ha-Elokim. So
it's interesting, again, the idea that a human being could here be
מתיר matir God's נדר. neder. Yes?
Who's
taking him to טורא דסיני Tura d'Sinai to say no?
The nomad, the Arab nomad.
So he took him to
the מתי מדבר. Metei Midbar. And then the חכמים Chachamim criticized him.
Right. Then he said, okay, forget these חכמים, Chachamim, let's go someplace
else. Yeah, is that what it says?
Yeah, I don't know if he said forget these חכמים Chachamim or
whatever, but yeah,
they must have all been on the same trip. I don't know
if these were separate travels or all one travel, but whatever.
But he keeps on going to different places with the nomad.
Exactly.
Yeah, alright, moving on. What do we make of that?
About the white scorpions?
I don't know. David, what do your notes say about the white
scorpions? Alright, we'll take a look, you'll tell us. Alright, now we
go on. Alright, moving on. רבנן, Rabbanan, by the way, it does
say מפר mefer and מפר mefer is about a husband and a
wife. התרת נדרים Hatarat Nedarim is about a בית דין. Beit Din.
So again, I do wonder whether it has echoes of that מדרש
Midrash of משה איש האלוהים. Moshe ish ha-Elokim.
And he could be מפר mefer a שבועה shvua because he was
at הר סיני? Har Sinai?
Connection between, I don't know, you mean why was the שבועה, shvua,
I was wondering that too, why was the שבועה shvua about גלות
galut being heard at הר סיני? Har Sinai? You would think the
שבועה, shvua, I understand maybe because they didn't keep תרי"ג מצוות, taryag
mitzvot, but you would also think that the שבועה shvua would be
heard at like the הר הבית, Har ha-Bayit, right, which something that
represents the חורבן. churban. But anyway, yeah, David, what do you have
there?
It refers to the רבנן Rabbanan who protected
the תורה, Torah,
but be careful that you warm yourself by their fire, you know.
Right, right, and their bite is harsh,
right, okay. Yeah, cause I mean actually that מדרש Midrash about the
חכמים Chachamim and like the bite of a scorpion, the sting of
a scorpion. Okay. Next story.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. המבול. ha-mabbul. רבנן אוי
לי למי לי. Rabbanan oy li lami li. אמר לי תא אחוי
לך בלועי דקורח, Amar li ta achvei lach beluei d'Korach,
let me go show you those the people of Korah's camp that
were swallowed up in the earth, like where the earth swallowed up
Korah's camp. חזא תרי ביזעי, Chaza trei biz'ei, so he saw, I
saw two cracks in the ground, והוו קא
מפקי קוטרא, v'hava ka mapki kutra, and smoke was rising out of
it. שקל גבבא דעמרא, Shakal gavava d'amra, so what I did was
to see how hot it was down there, is I took like
a wool, no,
עמרא amra is wool, I took like a clump of wool, that
was what I was looking for, a clump of wool, ואמשיכה במיה,
v'amshicha b'mayah, and I sort of submerged it in water, soaked it
in water, ודאעציתה
בראשה דרומחא, v'da-atzitah b'resha d'rumcha, and I sort of stuck it on
the top of a pole, ואייליה התם, v'aylei hatam, and I lowered
it down there, וכי אפיק, v'chi afik, and when I brought it
up, הוה איחרך איחרוכי, hava achrich ichruchi, it was singed, so clearly
it's pretty darn hot down there. אמר לי, Amar li, so now
this nomad said to me, אצית מה שמעת, atzit mah shamat, listen
closely to what's being said.
Okay, so so. And they, meaning we, the people
who are speaking בדאים, badayim, were liars. So this is, you know,
in the end, obviously, because they challenged Moshe's authority, and here they
are, in the, not only getting punished for their sins, and obviously
it's also a very great, graphic, this whole idea, imagery, that we
normally associate more with, like, a Christian imagery of, of hell, you
know, sort of down there and they're burning for their sins, right?
But anyway, but not only are they being punished, but they're also
acknowledging, you know, it's sort of like a,
you know, you know what is it, like, 1984 or whatever, you
know, where these, in these totalitarian regimes, that, like, before they execute
you, they make you, like, confess your crimes, right? So anyway, so
here they are, they, anyway, what?
The Inquisition tried to
do, oh yeah, get people to confess, okay. Anyway, so here they
were, they're admitting the truth of Moshe.
Yes. What's the גמרא's Gemara view about, like, you know, for generation
to generation, maybe an exception because these are בני קרח, Bnei Korach,
you know, they're rebellious, but in general what do they think happens
to people, like, you know, when they die, in hell, is it?
Well right, but this isn't exactly hell. So let's look at the
next slide. אמר לי, amar li, so then this shepherd, this nomad,
said to me, כל תלתין יומין, kol tlatzin yomin, every
thirty days, מהדרו לגיהנם להכא, mahadu l'Gehinnom l'hacha, they actually, you know,
most of the time they're in גיהנם, Gehinnom, they're not here, this
isn't גיהנם, Gehinnom, this is in the depths of the earth, like,
you know, the earth has a molten core or something, most of
the time they're somewhere else, they're wherever גיהנם Gehinnom is. Okay, but
once every month they come back here to the place of their
sin and to sort of acknowledge and, you know, the, the, you
know, and acknowledge their sin. כבשרא בגלחטא, k'vasra b'chalachta, the same way
every now and then you turn over a piece of meat that's
boiling in a pot, okay, you gotta get it, you know, both
sides, you gotta get it, whatever. So, so it sounds like actually
this might be, I don't know, hotter than גיהנם, Gehinnom, it's not
exactly clear to me how the punishment here.
No, or it's rotating, like, you know, and it rotates around the
earth and now you can hear it here.
Oh, maybe, you mean the word מהדר, mahader, but maybe, but I
thought it meant that they are sort of, yeah, turn, yeah, you're
right, like what does it mean to be turned over? Anyway, I'm
not exactly sure. Okay, anyway, moving on. ואמרי הכי, v'amri hachi, and
then they say this once they arrive here, משה ותורתו אמת והן
בדאי. Moshe v'Torato emet v'hen badaya. Okay. אמר לי, amar li, he
said to me, תא אחוי לך היכא דנשקי ארעא ורקיעא, ta achavi
lach heicha d'nashki ara v'rakia, I'm going to show you where heaven
and earth kiss, where there's a point that's so high that you
actually get access to the
heaven, all right, so אהדדי, ahadadi, they kiss one another, touch one
another. סלקא, saklasa, I was somewhere up there on some mountain, where
very high up in the Himalayas or whatever, okay, and I had
access to the heavens, you have to understand that they understood, right,
that the heavens were this רקיע, rakia, was, you know, was some
type of, like, this physical, you know, dome, right, that covered the
earth. So here he is, he's on some mountain top, okay, whoops,
I don't know what I did with that plus, he's on some
mountain top, and here is this physical dome, this רקיע, rakia, that
is, he's able to actually touch it. Okay. So שקלתה לסילתי, shaklasa
l'siltay, so I took my bread basket, you know, my knapsack, I
had put it down, אנחתה בכוותא דרקיע, asnachta b'chavsa d'rakia,
and I put it, there was a little hole right here, right,
you know, like the פסוק pasuk says by the מבול, mabul, וכל
ארבות השמים נשתחו, v'chol arubot hashamayim nishtachu,
so there was a little, there was a little window there, which
I don't know, maybe rain comes down, whatever comes down through that
window and I said, oh good, I need to put my knapsack
down somewhere, so I put my knapsack down here, okay, and in
that little hole. And then, עד דמצלינא, ad d'matzlina, now I had
to put it down because I had to דאווען, daven, I mean
what better place to דאווען daven than when you're right up right
next to heaven, okay, again, I don't know if the association of
רקיע, rakia, the,
I'm a little bit joking because רקיע rakia actually I think generally
means more, sort of, the physical sense of the sky, you know,
however they physically understood it as opposed to, like, שמים, shamayim, which
is heavens, which is where God is, okay. So anyway, but nevertheless,
he was at this high place, he wanted to דאווען, daven, maybe
it was just some מנחה mincha time came or something. So I
had to put down my bag, so I put it down in
that window. And by the time I was done דאוונינג, davening,
עד דבעיתי ולא אשכח אשכחיתה, ad d'baise v'lo ashkach ashkachita, I, you
know, I was looking for it and I couldn't find it, it
had somehow disappeared. I put it in that window and then it
disappeared. So אמינא ליה איכא גנבי הכא, amina lei eika ganvi hacha,
I said to him that, what, are there like, are there like
robbers here at top of the mountain top who took my bag?
So what, or maybe in heavens they're thieves, right?
That'd be even worse, right? There's a little sign up by this
window, we are not responsible for items left unattended. Okay. So
אמר לי amar li to me,
האי גלגלא דרקיע הוא דהדר. hai galgala d'rakia hu d'hadar. No, no,
no. That is the, the wheel of the רקיע rakia that turns
around. נטר עד למחר הכא ומשכחת לה. natar ad le-makhar hakha u-mashkhat
lah. I'll describe it in a minute. Wait until tomorrow and you'll
find it because basically what happens is the way it works is,
right, is that if you imagine, like, you know, it's also this
whole question about like why when you see stars, right, what happens
like you're seeing stars let's say at night and the stars seem
to move and then they appear at the same place at the
same. Anyway, so this whole big thing moves around and comes back,
you know, the earth is stable and the sky and the heavens
sort of move around with the stars and with the moon and
whatever it is, right, and maybe with the sun and that's why
the sun sets. The question is the sun moves independent of the
רקיע. rakia. So you put it in here, this whole thing, I
guess the window remained but the whole thing moved. So by now
your bag is over here. Okay. It's part of by tomorrow it'll
come back there and come get it tomorrow. Okay. So that's what
happened.
Do the windows stay put?
Yeah, I don't exactly get that. Maybe there's a window, you know,
the moving contraption is separate from the, you know, maybe
you went inside of itself but like there's like if you have
needles in a thing, I mean in that one the window's moving.
Oh yeah, that's I know what you're talking about.
Or you can imagine the thing where the window stays still and
you're moving the needles. Right.
But whatever. Yeah, you mean there's a cover, there's a cover that's
stationary and the moving thing moves underneath the cover. Like what?
Like a שבת Shabbat lamp.
A שבת Shabbat lamp. Yeah. Right.
So who was talking to him?
The, this Arab nomad that was showing him all the secrets of
the desert.
Okay but what do you make of this part? This red basket.
Oh yeah, I don't know. I don't know. Do you want to,
can you give it a whirl?
Well, it has to do with
that the, the Arab here, this is from the הגה, Hagah, is
the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara trying to get the תורה Torah scholars
to work in the world as well and then they should work.
And think about who gains wealth and who doesn't. It's all in
the hands of השם.
Hashem. Oh, okay. So the bread basket is פרנסה parnassah and that,
oh, and that, you know, and that's also like, you know, fortune.
It's like people sometimes rise and fall in terms of their worldly
fortune.
I see. Interesting. Okay. All right. Okay. רבי יוחנן משתעי. Rabbi Yochanan
mishtayei. Now we're done with the Arab nomad. Now we get rabbis
telling about their sea tales, about the things that occurred to them
when they were traveling by the sea and it's by the way
it's interesting the word משתעי. mishtayei. משתעי mishtayei was more like you
know, was told a story. It's a different type of a verb
than like רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar or whatever. Anyway, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan told a story. זמנא חדא, zimna chada, one time,
הוי קאזלינא בספינתא, havei ka-azlina be-sephinta, I was going on a boat,
וחזינא ההוא כוורא, ve-chazina hahu kavra, we're talking about again big fish.
I saw a particular fish or sea creature, דאפקי לרישיה מימא, de-aphki
le-reisha mi-yama,
its head came out of the ocean, ודמי עיניה כתרתי סיהרי, ve-dami
eineih ke-tray siharei,
and its eyes looked like two moons, ונפוץ מיא מתרתי זימיה, ve-naphutz
maya mi-tarti zimeih,
and water was flowing from its two nostrils, כתרתי נהרי דסורא, ke-tarti
naharei de-Sura,
like these two rivers of Sura. Okay, that's not such a fantastical
story.
רב ספרא משתעי. Rav Saphra mishtayei. רב ספרא Rav Saphra said. זמנא
חדא הוי קאזלינא בספינתא, zimna chada havei ka-azlina be-sephinta, once I was
going
on a boat, וחזינא ההוא כוורא, ve-chazina hahu kavra, and
I saw a fish or sea creature, דאפקי לרישיה
מימא, de-aphki le-reisha mi-yama, that stuck its head out of the ocean,
והוה ליה קרני, ve-havei lei karnei,
and it had horns, ודחקיק עליה, ve-chakik aleih,
and were written on the horns, אנא בריה קלה שבים, ana birya
kala she-ba-yam, I am just a small creature of the sea, והוינא,
ve-havina, and this little small creature was, תלת מאה פרסי, tlath mea
parsei, 300 parasangs, ואזלינא לפומא דלויתן. ve-azlina le-phuma de-Livyathan. Oh actually,
I'm sorry, this is actually written on the horns. I am merely
a small creature of the sea and I am 300 parasangs long,
ואזלינא לפומא דלויתן, ve-azlina le-phuma de-Livyathan,
and I am going into the mouth of the לויתן. Livyathan. I'm
just לויתן's Livyathan breakfast. Okay, so you can imagine how big the
לויתן Livyathan is. Okay. אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. ההוא עיזא
דימא הוא. Hahu iza de-yama hu. Now the fact that it had
horns shows me that that was the goat of the sea. We
have sea horses, they had sea goats. Okay, דבחישא, de-bhachisha, then it
uses the horns to like dig in the ground of the, you
know, of the ocean in order to find its food, דבחישא, de-bhachisha,
ואית ליה קרני, ve-ith lei karnei, and that's why it has horns.
רבי יוחנן משתעי. Rabbi Yochanan mishtayei. Now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said.
זמנא חדא הוי קאזלינא בספינתא, zimna chada havei ka-azlina be-sephinta,
once I was going on a boat, וחזינא ההיא קרטליתא, ve-chazina ha-hi
kartalisa, דהוו קא מיתבי בה אבנים טובות, de-havu ka-mithbi bah avanim tovoth,
I saw a certain chest like a box, you know. A treasure
chest. Exactly. That were affixed to it these amazing jewels, ומרגליות, u-margalios,
והדרי לה מיני דחורי, ve-hadrei lah minei de-chavrei,
and were surrounding it certain types of fish, דמיקרי כרשא, de-mikrei karsha,
which were called karsha. I'm thinking this means sharks. Okay. You mean
sharks? Shark, a shark, you know. So there you go, the classic
treasure chest surrounded with sharks.
That's the Hebrew word in modern Hebrew
for shark is, okay, כרשה? karsha? כרשה. karsha. כרשא Karsha כרש Kersh
כרש. Kersh. Aha. Okay,
so we got to go get the treasure chest. So נחשיש בר
אמוראי Nachshish bar Amorei לאתויי, le-atuyei, so a diver that's the word
for a diver, we have it in other גמרות. Gemaras. בר אמוראי,
bar Amorei, I don't know where that word, how that comes to
mean, I don't know, but it means a diver. Yeah, maybe.
A diver went down לאתויי le-atuyei to retrieve it, ורגיש ve-ragish and
the shark sensed that somebody was coming to take the treasure chest,
ובעי לשמטיה לאטמיה u-ba'i leshamtei le-atmei
and it wanted to basically tear out his leg, you know, the
shark wanted to bite off his leg. שדא זיקא דחלא, shada zika
de-hala,
so this diver threw a like a flask of vinegar, ונח ve-nah
and it calmed the fish down, it stopped the shark from trying
to attack it. So rather than having one of those harpoon things,
you got a vinegar, yes.
בר אמוראי bar Amorei is a diver, yes, at Latin mare means
the
ocean.
Really?
Interesting.
M-A-R-E. Mare, אמוראי. Amorei. Interesting, it's a Latin Spanish word, interesting. Also
used for the moon,
when they you know the
map of the moon, the mare this, mare that, the sea of
such and such. Oh,
interesting. Okay, there you go. Thank you. I actually heard עניינא דיומא
inyan de-yoma of פסח, Pesach, why is horseradish I this might be
complete נארישקייט narishkeit what I heard, so this is maybe a popular
etymology but why is horseradish called horseradish? What does it have to
do with horses? That apparently it was called the radish of the
mare, of the sea, because I don't know, maybe it grew by
it and somehow it became mare which was horse or something. You
can go ahead and see if that's correct. Anyway, but that's interesting
for the בר אמוראי. bar Amorei. Okay, so anyway, ושדא זיקא ונח.
ve-shada zika ve-nah. נפק בת קול navak bat kol אמר להן, amar
lan, now so now he got the shark he pacified the shark,
you know, neutralized the shark, wanted to retrieve the treasure chest, a
heavenly voice came out and
אמר להן: amar lan: מאי עסקייכו בהדי קרטיליתא דדביתהו דרבי חנינא בן
דוסא? mai isaikhu bahadei kartelita de-dveiteh de-Rabbi Hanina ben Dosa? That is
a treasure chest for the wife of רבי חנינא בן דוסא. Rabbi
Hanina ben Dosa. She's going to get that in the future time.
She was very righteous and never wanted to benefit from her share
in the world to come. That is to be stored for her.
דעתידה דשדיא תכלת בה לצדיקי לעלמא דאתי. de-atida de-shadya tekhelet bah le-tzaddikai
le-alma de-atei. She in the end is going to now I don't
exactly get
this knit תכלת, tekhelet, you know, sew תכלת tekhelet in it for
the צדיקים Tzaddikim in the world to come. What does that mean?
That means it's stored with these precious cloths. And does תכלת tekhelet
here mean ציצית? tzitzit? I mean we just saw before that תכלת
tekhelet means ציצית. tzitzit. So I'm not exactly sure what the point
of that is.
But they make it that it's in the ocean.
That's where you store the treasure chest for the world to come
as opposed to in the heaven. Right. I don't know. David, you
got anything interesting in the notes? תכלת tekhelet comes from the ocean.
You'd have to read it more slowly. What? Oh, תכלת tekhelet comes
from the ocean. Ah, that's a good point, right right. But she's
in the future... Yeah I don't know, what is she going to
be? She's going to be the seamstress in the future? She's going
to make the ציצית tzitzit in the future?
She's going to find the תכלת tekhelet so we can start work.
Oh, she's going to find the תכלת. tekhelet. But in time of
the גמרא Gemara they knew what where to get תכלת. tekhelet.
Knowing that we're not going to...
Oh, okay, there you go. Okay, רב יהודה הינדוא Rav Yehuda Hindua
it has this idea about
someone wanting to get something they don't deserve.
Well that obviously, that's right. But what about the wife and the
תכלת? tekhelet?
Okay, so they have that story about, you know about she refused
the gift, she
refused the gift from the world to come, right. רב יהודה הינדוא,
Rav Yehuda Hindua, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the Hindu or not Hindu
but the Indian from India, right. I mean Hinduism really just means
the religion of the India. Okay, the Indian from India, told the
following story: זימנא חדא הוינא אזלינא בספינתא zimna hada havai azina be-sfinta
once I was going on a boat, וחזינא ההוא אבן טבא ve-hazina
hu evan tava and I saw a beautiful
jewel, דהוה הדיר ליה תנינא de-hava hadir leh tanina that was surrounded
by a sea serpent. נחית בר אמוראי לאתויי nahis bar Amorei le-atuyei
so we sent down some diver to retrieve it, so the whole
gear diving for buried treasure is a very ancient theme. אתא
תנינא קא בעי למבלעיה ata tanina ka ba'i le-mivleh leh so then
the sea serpent came and wanted to swallow up the diver. I'm
sorry, not only the diver, קא בעי למבלעיה לספינתא ka ba'i le-mivleh
le-sfinta was going to now attack the entire boat. אתא פישקנצא, ata
pishkantsa, you might remember the פישקנצא, pishkantsa, we had this before, the
raven that came that ate the that ate you know the sea
serpent. What did the sea serpent eat in that story before?
A big frog.
A big frog, right right. Okay, so came this raven, פשחיה לרישיה
pashcha le-reisha cut off the head of the sea serpent. There is
actually what is that bird that you that actually
there's a certain bird that's good for attacking is it scorpions or
something? What am I thinking of? Anyway, okay, anyway, that but this
idea that there's like a bird that attack can attack like dan-
you know or certain anyway whatever I don't know. Anyway, the sea
serpent came, cut off the head of the sea I'm sorry, the
raven came, cut off the head of the sea serpent. Now פסקה
לרישיה, paskeh l'reisheh, יתהפכו מיא והוו דמא, ithapechu maya v'havu dama, and
the water turned into blood. So there you go, echoing the מכת
דם, Makat Dam, פסחים. Pesachim. Okay.
Also, maybe we can hold this thing as a metaphor for פסח,
Pesach, you know.
Instead of חד גדיא. Chad Gadya. Right?
חד גדיא, Chad Gadya, well that we mentioned last time. By the
way though, thinking about this, there is a case where, which פסוק,
pasuk, where is it in נביא Navi where פרעה Paroh says, תנין
הגדול? Tanin HaGadol? הרובץ בתוך יאוריו. ha'rovetz betoch ye'orav. Yeah, no, but
פרעה, Paroh, there's a later פרעה Paroh in תנ"ך Tanakh that compares
himself to a great תנין, Tanin, right? Do people know what I'm
talking about?
יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Yes. Who? Right, so anyway, so here you have a
תנין Tanin being cut off and turning into blood.
Okay, let me just see if I can quickly find it asking
Rabbi Google. What are you searching for?
תנין הגדול. Tanin HaGadol.
Alright, I'm not finding it.
אני יאורי ואני עשיתני. Ani ye'ori va'ani asitani. Yeah, okay anyway. Alright,
moving on, especially if תנין Tanin is a crocodile. Anyway, so this
could anyway, this maybe is
some echo of that whole story. Anyway, cut off its head and
the whole water turned to blood, והוו דמא. v'havu dama.
אתא תנינא חבריה, ata Tanina Chavra, so then its friend sea serpent
or crocodile came, שקלה, shaklasah, took the head that had been severed,
ואתייה, v'ataylei, and put it back on the body.
Let me just finish.
Took the stone and hung
it on the dead mush-man's, that's what,
ah, as opposed to took the head and hung it. I see,
took something. I thought it meant took the head. Wait, okay, wait,
let me just finish the story. Either took the head or took
the stone. I thought it meant took re-affixed the head to the
body, וחיה. v'chaya. And then the sea monster or the crocodile, you
know, came back to life.
Let's just finish this. הדר כאבי בעו לספינתא, hadar ka'avei ba'ei l'sefineta,
so now that the sea monster came back to life, it wanted
to once again destroy the boat because we were still trying to
retrieve the stone. הדר אתא צפורא, hadar ata tzipora, so then another
bird came, פסקה לרישיה, paskeh l'reisheh, cut off its head,
שקלוה להא אבן טבא, shaklu'ah l'hai even tava, ושדיוה לספינתא, v'shadyu'ah l'sefineta,
so and then it took, so he, this might be now the
diver, no, could be, I think the diver, it's not clear. Now
took the stone and put it on the boat. We had a
moment, he had a like a שעת הכושר, sha'as hakosher, especially if
the previous read was that the stone allowed the other the sea
monster to, you know, to resuscitate. So now you want to get
rid of the stone before the sea monster comes back alive. So
after the second bird cut off its head a second time, got
the stone on the boat. הוו הני צפורי מליחי בהדן, havu hani
tziprei melichi bahadeinu, we had stored with us in the boat for
our meals, we had
some salted birds.
ואותבינהו עלייהו, u'shvinu'ah alaihu, we put the stone on the birds, okay,
so maybe this is also why it was assumed before that it
was the stone that revived the sea monster because we put the
stone on the birds, שחו פרחו להו בהדה, shacho parcho lah behada,
and then the birds came back to life and they took the
stone and they flew away. So we didn't, so this was a
stone, I guess, of תחיית המתים, techiyat hametim, a type of a
תחיית המתים techiyat hametim type of a stone. Okay, what was that,
Harry Potter and the
Sorcerer- and it also made me think of the whole, what was
that first early Harry Potter with the Basilisk? The Basilisk or whatever,
okay, anyway, so that's what it clearly presages is all the Harry
Potter. What's the פסוק pasuk you have there, Michael?
No, this is just פרעה מלך מצרים, Paroh Melech Mitzrayim,
it doesn't say which פרעה. Paroh. But it doesn't say תנין הגדול?
Tanin HaGadol?
That's the one I quoted there. התנין הגדול הרובץ בתוך יאוריו אשר
אמר לי יאורי
ואני עשיתני.
Ha-Tanin HaGadol ha-rovetz betoch ye'orav asher amar li
ye'ori va'ani asitani.
Right, but it doesn't use the word תנין, Tanin, it just says...
התנין הגדול. Ha-Tanin HaGadol.
התנין הגדול, Ha-Tanin HaGadol,
right, so פרעה Paroh is referred to as התנין הגדול, Ha-Tanin HaGadol,
especially if תנין Tanin means crocodile. So one wonders, right, what is
this? Is this about that we cut off, you know, there was
יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, you know, the splitting, we went through, it's
in the ocean or whatever, but you know, but then the other,
but then the other powerful nations come and you know, and they
re-, you know, and they sort of, you know, conquer, you know,
whatever, what's the word I'm looking for, not exiles, what? No, well,
well, re-animate yes, but I'm saying, you know, they, you know, we
don't remain free in that way. We become, you know, resubject to
them, you know, and so on, and so and the ultimately the
search for, you know, the תחיית המתים techiyat hametim and the future
whatever that's being withheld from us until future time. That's my פירוש
perush on this. Yes.
I have this based on לבן Lavan in בראשית Bereishit 31:9, the
ship is the person and the precious stone is the intellect and
then the יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
Oh, I like my explanation much better. No, I'm serious, there's these
echoes of יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, we seem to destroy them, we
go through the ocean, right, it's all about getting to, you know,
the ultimate redemption, the stone which brings life, but ultimately, you know,
we get exiled again and every time we think we have it
in our grasp it gets taken away from us. That's my פשט.
pshat. Yes.
Coming from heaven and having to do and then in the end
השם, Hashem, we're enslaved to השם.
Hashem. Oh, interesting. So השם Hashem is the one that comes and
destroys the sea monster for us, but that in the end, right...
oh, freedom.
Right. There you go, beautiful. All right, we should be writing our
פירוש peirush on the
הגדה Hagadda here.
I was thinking about that too. I was thinking about that too,
about the birds that came down by אברהם. Avraham. Okay, תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. מה... now we actually have a ברייתא. מעשה ברבי אליעזר
וברבי יהושע שהיו באים בספינה. Maaseh b'Rabbi Eliezer u'v'Rabbi Yehoshua she'hayu ba'im
b'sefina. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, they were
both one generation before רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, they were רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva's רבנים. rabbeim. They were coming in a boat. והיה רבי
אליעזר ישן ורבי יהושע נעור. V'haya Rabbi Eliezer yashen v'Rabbi Yehoshua ne'or.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was sleeping and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was
awake. ונזדעזע רבי יהושע. V'nizda'aze'a Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua started
trembling. וניעור רבי אליעזר. V'ni'or Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer woke
up. What's the matter? אמר לו מה זה יהושע מפני מה נזדעזעת.
Amar lo mah zeh Yehoshua mipnei mah nizda'azata.
Why did you start trembling? אמר לו מאור גדול ראיתי בים. Amar
lo ma'or gadol ra'iti ba'yam. I saw like a huge luminary in
the ocean. אמר לו שמא עינו של לויתן ראית. Amar lo shema
eino shel livyatan ra'ita. Ah, maybe you just saw one of the
eyes of the לויתן. livyatan. שכתוב עיניו כעפעפי שחר. Shekasuv einav k'afapei
shachar.
Its eyes are like the eyelids of the morning, like I guess
like the sun, like the luminary. אמר רב אשי אמר לי הונא
בר נתן. Amar Rav Ashi amar li Huna bar Nasan. הונא בר
נתן Huna bar Nasan said to me, so now we're going to
sort of... we've opened up a little bit and we've already mentioned
it before, the לויתן livyatan theme, so that's going to come up.
Okay, so אמר לי הונא בר נתן זימנא חדא הוה קאזילנא במדברא.
Amar li Huna bar Nasan zimna chada hava ka'azilna b'midbara. Once I
was going in the wilderness. והוה אטמא דבישרא בהדן. V'hava atma d'visra
behadan. And we had like a, you know, a thigh of meat
with us. פתחנא ונקרינא. Pasachna v'nakrina. We opened it up, we removed
the fat and the גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. ואנחנא אעשבי. V'anachna a'isvei.
And we put it down on the grass. אדמייתינא ציבי. Admayisina tzivei.
Until we could get some chips of wood to make a fire
and to roast it. חלים אטמא. Chalim atma. And while we were
doing that, the leg revived, like sort of restored, it started to
reanimate, but like the way we had opened it and taken it
out, it sort of closed itself up. Okay. It was another like...
it was another like of a little תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim type
of a you know, something that had power to revive things. Okay.
Literally it means it was healed. חלים אטמא. Chalim atma. וטוינא. V'tavina.
And then we roasted it. כי הדרן לבתר תריסר ירחי שתא. Ki
hadran l'vasar treisar yarchei shata. When we returned after twelve months, חזינא
להני גומרי דהוו קמלחשי. chazina l'hanei gumrei d'hava k'malachshei. We saw the
coals that they were still whispering, they were still burning. Okay. כי
אתאי לקמיה דאמימר. Ki asai l'kamei d'Amemar. When I came to אמימר,
Amemar, אמר לי הוא עשבא סמתרי הוה. Amar li hu isba samteri
hava. That grass was this special grass called סמתרי, samteri, which has
this powerful restorative powers. So I guess it wasn't as good as
the stone that actually brought the dead back to life, but actually
it has some healing powers. והנו גומרי דרתמא הוו. V'hanu gumrei d'risma
havu. And those coals were a רתם rosam tree.
A רתם rosam wood burns...
there's another story, רתם rosam where it burns very long.
Yeah, it burns for a very long... there's another סוגיא sugya in
סוכות Succos where they went to the מדבר, midbar, did the pilgrimage
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and they come back a year later
and the רתם rosam is still burning. Burning. Oh, there you go.
רתם. Rosam.
So it's called a broom tree.
Broom tree. Interesting. Okay, let's read a little bit more. ויברא אלקים
את התנינים הגדולים. Vayivra Elokim es hatanninim hagedolim. Now we're going to
get into the whole, you know, לויתן livyatan discussion. God created the
huge sea monsters. הכא תרגימו ארזילי דימא. Hacha targimu arzeilei d'yama. Here
we translated as the, I don't know, antelope of the sea. רבי
יוחנן אמר זה לויתן נחש בריח ולויתן נחש עקלתון. Rabbi Yochanan amar
zeh livyatan nachash bariach v'livyatan nachash akalasson. This is the לויתן, livyatan,
the snake of the
rod, and the לויתן, livyatan, the curved לויתן, livyatan, which is identified
as the male and the female לויתן. livyatan. You can figure out
the imagery. שנאמר ביום ההוא יפקוד השם בחרבו הקשה. Shene'emar bayom hahu
yifkod Hashem b'charbo hakasha. That day God will, you know, will visit
with his hard sword. And the end of the פסוק pasuk is
את לויתן נחש
בריח ואת לויתן נחש עקלתון. es livyatan nachash bariach v'es livyatan nachash
akalasson. I think it's the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב כל מה שברא הקדוש ברוך הוא בעולמו זכר
ונקבה בראם. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kol mah shebara HaKadosh Baruch
Hu b'olamo zachar u'nekeiva bera'am. Everything God created in His world, male
and female He created them. Okay, which is pretty funny because there
are some animals, there are not... whatever, some microbes or whatever, right,
that... not just microbes. Aren't there things like lizards?
Lizards are only... yeah anyway okay.
What? Worms. Worms are what? Are both male and female at the
same time. Aha. But okay. אף לויתן נחש בריח ולויתן נחש עקלתון
זכר ונקבה בראם. Af livyatan nachash bariach v'livyatan nachash akalasson zachar u'nekeiva
bera'am. Even the לויתן, livyatan, the snake of the rod, and the
לויתן, livyatan, the curved לויתן, livyatan, male and female He created them.
ואלמלא נזקקין זה לזה מחריבין כל העולם כולו. V'ilmalei nizkakkin zeh la-zeh
machrivin kol olam kulo. If they would ever actually
copulate, they would destroy the entire world with all of their progeny.
Okay, מה עשה הקדוש ברוך הוא? mah asa HaKadosh Baruch Hu? So
what was God going to do? Meaning, the point that He created
male and female, and I think there's a power to this is,
because we're going to see, they were... even though they were never
going to be allowed to copulate, so what would be the point
of creating a male and female? Right, there's a sense of like
if you want to call it yin and yang, there's a sense
of like two parts of a whole that everything has something that,
you know, complements it, makes it whole and so on. Even the
לויתן livyatan that never would actually be able to- They were still
created male and female. What did God do to prevent them from,
you know, from getting together? So הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu
סירס את הזכר siras es hazachar he castrated the male והרג הנקבה
veharag hanekeivah and he killed the female. Now of course if he
castrated the male why did he have to kill the female, but
okay, we'll see about that. ומלחה לצדיקים לעתיד לבוא umalachah latzaddikim le'asid
lavo and he salted it for the righteous for the future that
they would now have some nice herring made out of the female
Leviathan. Okay שנאמר shenemar
והרג את התנין אשר בים veharag es hatannin asher bayam he destroyed
the sea monster, so it's only singular as opposed to תנינים, tanninim,
so God created two, but he killed one. He killed the female,
he let the male live.
Okay.
Now ואף בהמות בהררי אלף veaf behemoth behararei alef there's a פסוק
pasuk in תהילים Tehillim that's referring to the animals on the thousand
mountains, which is understood by חז"ל Chazal as a reference to, you
know, this huge animal the שור הבר Shor HaBar that we'll also
right in the עתיד לבוא asid lavo we're going to have a
very good shmorg. It's going to be for those that like meat
we'll have the שור הבר, Shor HaBar, for those that like fish
we'll have the לויתן, Livyasan, okay, so anyway I don't know about
the vegetarians, you know, anyway there's a certain joke about whatever which
I'll tell it offline about that anyway, okay. ואף בהמות בהררי אלף
veaf behemoth behararei alef even those huge beasts that also will be
for the future for us to feast on in the future. זכר
ונקבה בראם zachar unekeivah bera'am were male and female and they also
were never going to be able to copulate, but nevertheless they were
created male and female. ואלמלא נזקקין זה לזה ve'ilmalei nizkakim zeh lazeh
were they ever were they'd ever copulate מחריבין כל העולם כולו machrivin
kol ha'olam kulo they destroy the whole world. מה עשה הקדוש ברוך
הוא mah asah HaKadosh Baruch Hu what did God do? סירס הזכר
siras hazachar he castrated the male וצינן הנקבה vetzinan hanekeivah he cooled
off the female. So at first I thought this meant he put
her in like cold storage, you know, keep your meat in a
refrigerator,
you know, it's better, I'd rather have refrigerated meat than salted meat.
But apparently it means cooled her in a sense that to not
make her able to bear children, but she still kept her alive.
Of course why you needed to do that once you castrated the
male is not exactly clear. Okay ושמרה לצדיקים לעתיד לבוא ushmarah latzaddikim
le'asid lavo and also there the female's being kept for the righteous
for the future to eat from. I don't know I guess we're
not going to eat from the males. Okay שנאמר shenemar as it
says הנה נא כוחו במתניו hineh na kocho bemosnav its strength is
in its loins זה זכר zeh zachar that is the male ואונו
בשרירי בטנו ve'ono beshirirei bitno and its strength is in its like
you know in the I'm not the
בשרירי beshirirei how do they translate that word?
Strength is in its loins, this refers to the men,
yeah, and what's the next part of the verse?
And its power in the navel of its belly.
Navel, oh, the center of its belly זה נקבה zeh nekeivah obviously
in terms of like referring to the womb and so on. Right.
So anyway and that refers to these animals. So now just to
end this one story התם נמי ליסרסיה לזכר ולצננה לנקבה hasam nami
lisarseih lezachar uletzinneh lenekeivah so why for the Leviathan did God have
to kill the female Leviathan, why not just cool her down? דגי
פריצי dagei pritzei no fish are very are very promiscuous. So even
if she were to be cooled down she would still want to
copulate. Now I don't know who she's going to copulate with, maybe
with other fish that are not the Leviathan I what can I
tell you. Anyway with other maybe it's a mammal it's like a
whale. Anyway but maybe with other fish that are not her mate
because the male is castrated. Anyway so cooling her down would not
have worked. ולא עביד איפכא vela avid ipcha okay, so why not,
you know, kill the male
and have the female alive? So the גמרא Gemara says
איבעית אימא ibeis eima if you want I could
say נקבה מליחא מעלי nekeivah melicha ma'alei no because the female fish
a salted female fish tastes better than salted male fish, so we
want the better fish for the future. איבעית אימא ibeis eima and
if you want I could say כיון דכתיב לויתן זה יצרת לשחק
בו keivan deksiv livyasan zeh yatzarta lesachek bo you created this Leviathan
to play with, and according to in the גמרא בברכות Gemara BeBrachos
it says God leaves one hour of the day to have, you
know, to just I don't know even God needs entertainment, so to
play with the Leviathan, so since God is going to be playing
with the Leviathan so בהדי נקבה לאו אורח ארעא bahadi nekeivah lav
orech ara it wouldn't be appropriate for God who is cast as
male to be playing with the female Leviathan. Okay so the גמרא
Gemara says okay fine, now we get why that's what you did
for the Leviathan, but הכא נמי לילמלה לנקבה hacha nami leimlechah lenekeivah
fine, but now let's get to the big the big, you know,
ox or whatever it is, so why not there too, why not
salt the female, why are you cooling down the female, why not
kill her and salt her? כוורא מליחא מעלי kavara melicha ma'alei no,
salted fish tastes good. בישרא מליחא לא מעלי bisra melicha lo ma'alei
salted meat is not as good. Some people like it, you know,
they like their whatever their beef jerky, but you know fresh meat
tastes better. Okay I think we will stop there for now. All
right. All right.